So בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is י"ב. yud bet.
We are finishing up the discussion here about the status of sanctifying
one limb of an animal as a קרבן, korban, and we pick
up on the bottom of י"א
עמוד ב',
yud aleph
amud bet, 1, 2, 3, 6 lines from the bottom, middle of
the line. בעי מיניה אביי, ba'ei minei Abaye, it probably should be
מרבה, me'Rabba, אביי Abaye asked רבה, Rabba, which is his rebbe: הקדיש
עור מהו בעבודה? hikdish ora mahu ba'avoda?
What if you only sanctify the leather, the skin of it? Presumably,
this is according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir that say you can sanctify only a part of an animal
without it all becoming sanctified, although the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says
it might even be according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi because the
skin is never offered up, so maybe רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi would
say that the status of the skin doesn't affect the rest of
the animal, which is interesting. Anyway, so you have only the skin
sanctified. Can you now, can you go ahead and work the animal?
So presumably, the question is, I mean, you might have actually thought,
although the גמרא Gemara is going to say the opposite, that it's
not asking about shearing because shearing definitely would affect the skin because
it's something done against the skin. But maybe when you work an
animal, maybe it doesn't really affect the leather, affects other parts of
the animal, its health and so on. But the גמרא Gemara is
actually going to assume the opposite, that shearing certainly would not have
any impact,
and the question is how about the working, does that have an
impact? So let's take a look. That way it's very similar to
the question asked yesterday. So let's take a look. תא שמע, ta
shma, come and hear: אומר מה שבמעיה של זו עולה מותר בגיזה
ואסור בעבודה. omer ma she'b'me'ah shel zo olah mutar b'giza v'asur b'avoda.
If you sanctify the fetus of an animal, right, which was all
of yesterday's discussion,
then you can shear the animal because it has no impact on
the fetus, and you can't work it, משום דכחיש עובר שבה, mishum
d'kachish ubar she'bah, because working it will weaken the fetus inside, so
you might say the act of working actually is done to or
affects the fetus, but shearing is not done to or does not
affect the fetus. So therefore, and the assumption being that the same
would be true here, that working would affect the skin, although that
part is not spelled out. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said
back to him, maybe that's not relevant. כי קתני אסור בעבודה מדרבנן.
ki k'tani asur b'avoda m'drabbanan. No, maybe it's only, that's only Rabbinic
because you're not actually working the animal itself, you're only working the
mother, and maybe therefore it's only Rabbinic. And therefore I'm asking whether
biblically it would be a problem when it's only the skin. So
he says back, אי הכי אפילו בגיזה נמי תיתסר. ei hachi afilu
b'giza nami titsar. No, if it's just Rabbinic, we would forbid everything.
Not necessarily. אמר ליה עבודה דמיכחש גזרו בה רבנן גיזה דלא מיכחש
לא גזרו בה רבנן. amar lei avoda d'michachash gazru bei rabanan giza
d'lo michachash lo gazru bei rabanan. No, even if it's only Rabbinic,
working the animal again with the, if the fetus is sanctified, weakens
it, so there the Rabbis said don't work the mother because that
has an impact on the fetus, but shearing, which does not weaken
it, which has no impact on the fetus, they did not make
a גזירה. gezeira. So you can't prove because maybe that whole thing
is Rabbinic. Now again, it doesn't exactly explain what the nature of
his question was by the skin. You know, רש"י Rashi says, let
me just check רש"י Rashi again,
עבודה מכחיש ליה לעור, avoda machish lei l'ora, that the skin weakens,
that if you do work with the animal, somehow the skin is
affected. And if that's true, then basically the answer is okay, then
based on what we found out by this case by the fetus,
we know it's definitely forbidden Rabbinically, we want to know if it's
forbidden biblically. And why would I have thought that this might be
different? Not clear, I mean if the skin is sanctified,
you know, the fact that we're focusing on the skin makes it
sound like it's something special, it's somehow different than sanctifying a limb.
There's some reason why he's pointing out the skin, which is not
really fleshed out here in the גמרא. Gemara. So there are a
couple of possibilities. One possibility, like I said, is what the שיטה
מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says, that it's even רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi might
agree by the skin you can sanctify the skin without the rest
of the animal because it's not something that's offered up as a
קרבן. korban. My inclination, although this is not what רש"י Rashi says,
it would have been to go the opposite way, would have been
to say that the skin is not impacted by working the animal.
The animal might get skinnier, it might get weaker, but the skin
is not impacted by so much by working the animal. And therefore
the question is, what is the status by working it if it
doesn't really have too much of an impact on the skin?
What?
What about the animal working when a woman is pregnant to
work?
Nobody is saying the animal can't work, the question is how the
impact is. Right, but that's by the way is also a good
point. The assumption that working affects the fetus and weakens the fetus
is also funny, right? You'd say exercise actually would be good for
the fetus. So right. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara ends that.
Now we move on.
Maybe the yoke affects the skin.
What? The yoke, depending on if it's a cow to work or
if it's a sheep or whatever, right.
If it's a yoke.
Right, that's an interesting point. Okay, anyway, בעי מיניה, ba'ei minei, now
we're going to get on to a slightly different issue. Okay, that
was really a wrap-up of, that was parallel to the last case
we did yesterday. Now, בעי מיניה. ba'ei minei. Abaye asked רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef.
So we're still within these sort of splitting things, but in a
slightly from a different perspective. היו שלמים וולדה חולין. Hayu shelamim u-vladah
chullin.
Let's say you sanctified the mother as a שלמים shelamim and you
excluded the fetus because as we said, right, you could separate the
mother from the fetus according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan or you
could sanctify the mother and then it became pregnant afterwards, it wasn't
pregnant when you sanctified it, assuming that the fetus only becomes sanctified
at the moment of birth, a child of a קרבן, korban, not
while it's in utero.
So you have the mother is a שלמים shelamim and the child
is חולין. chullin. ושחטה בפנים, V'shachtah bifnim, and you shechted it as
a קרבן. korban. So now you, as you remember, this is very
similar to a case we had yesterday, shechting a חטאת chatas and
finding a child inside. So now that we're saying is now not
sanctified. מהו? Mahu? What is the status of the child? למאן דאמר
ולדי קדשים בהוייתן הן קדושין, L'man d'amar vladei kodashim b'havayatan hen kedoshin,
assuming that children of קדשים kodashim only become sanctified when they're born,
this was never born, so this was unsanctified. So what's the question?
ליהוי חולין בעזרה או לא? Lihavei chullin ba-azarah o lo? Is it
חולין בעזרה chullin ba-azarah or not? What is the status of this
animal?
Meaning, have you transgressed the prohibition of חולין בעזרה? chullin ba-azarah? Presumably,
let's say you knew that the animal was pregnant, okay, otherwise you
know, what do you mean pregnant? You were an אונס, oness, who
knows? But presumably you knew it was pregnant. So you knew that
by slaughtering it, there would be a non-sanctified animal in the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And it's not just that you're bringing a non-sanctified
animal in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Actually, it seems to be
a very specific question. The שחיטה shechitah on the mother worked for
the child. So you had an, you had the effect of שחיטה
shechitah on this חולין, chullin, but you never did the act of
שחיטה shechitah to the חולין. chullin. The physical act was done to
the mother, not to the child. And that seems to be the
question. If you did, the physical act was not done to it,
but you resulted in it being halachically shechted. Is that considered shechting
חולין בעזרה? chullin ba-azarah? What a great question. Were you allowed to
bring it? No, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
No, that's not the question. Not allowed to bring it as a
קרבן, korban, you're allowed to physically bring it in. There's a lot
of תוספות Tosafos that discuss that there are cases where you have
non-sanctified things in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. You can't do עבודה
avodah related stuff with חולין בעזרה. chullin ba-azarah. So you didn't do
the act of שחיטה, shechitah, but it resulted in being shechted.
Do you have this in, I'm surprised it wasn't in זבחים Zevachim
when we had all this.
Yeah, I know, it's so funny that sometimes, you know, the way
the locus of certain questions. Okay.
אמר ליה. Amar leih.
So רבא Rava said, sorry, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said back
to אביי, Abaye, מי קרינא ביה כי ירחק ממך המקום וזבחת? Mi
karina beih ki yirchak mimcha hamakom v'zavachta? No. So he said, rather
than sort of getting to the conceptual issue, he said, look, the
פסוק pasuk says where do we learn out you're not allowed to
bring חולין בעזרה? chullin ba-azarah? Because it says if you're far away
from the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, that's where you should shecht your
non-sanctified things, not in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But this, presumably,
so meaning the point was you weren't supposed to shecht, do the
שחיטה shechitah here. But here the mother was a שלמים, shelamim, so
you were supposed to do the שחיטה shechitah here. So since you
were supposed to do the שחיטה shechitah on the mother, you can't
say I didn't, I did anything wrong, because that's where you're supposed
to do the שחיטה. shechitah. So he sort, okay. I mean the
way רש"י Rashi frames it is האי לא יכול לשחוט בהמה זו
אלא בעזרה. Hai lo yachol lishchot behemah zu ela ba-azarah. The פסוק
pasuk is telling me you should have shechted it somewhere else, but
I couldn't have shechted it somewhere else, I had to shecht the
mother in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so I did not transgress.
Which doesn't exactly directly answer the conceptual question, right? It doesn't say,
well, the act versus the result, it just says look, if you
have to shecht the mother here, then you're within, then that's what
the תורה, Torah, then the תורה Torah allows that. The תורה Torah
is only telling you when you could have done it somewhere else.
Okay, now אביי Abaye isn't done though. בעי מיניה אביי מרב יוסף.
Ba'ei mineih Abayei mei-Rav Yosef. He asked the following question to רב
יוסף. Rav Yosef. היא חולין וולדה שלמים. Hi chullin v'vladah shelamim. Let's
reverse it. The mother is חולין chullin and the child is שלמים,
shelamim, according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that you can sanctify the
fetus directly. ושחטה בחוץ, V'shachtah bachutz, and shechted it out of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So it's the same point. Now you shechted
קדשים בחוץ, kodashim bachutz, but you didn't really shecht קדשים בחוץ. kodashim
bachutz. The act of שחיטה shechitah was done to the mother, which
wasn't קדשים, kodashim, but it resulted in the child, which was קדשים,
kodashim, being shechted. So is it an איסור issur of שחיטת קדשים
בחוץ shechitas kodashim bachutz when you didn't do an act of שחיטה
shechitah to the קדשים, kodashim, but you did the result of שחיטה
shechitah to the קדשים? kodashim? Because now the child is considered like
it's shechted. You know, this is such a great quest, it's like
the type of questions like אחרונים acharonim ask, you know, it's like
the type of מנחת חינוך Minchas Chinuch and Taph, you know, and
חזון איש Chazon Ish and חכם צבי Chacham Tzvi and stuff, you
know. So okay, is it about the act of שחיטה shechitah or
the result of שחיטה? shechitah? מי מחייב עלה משום שחוטי חוץ או
לא? Mi mechayev alah mishum shechutei chutz o lo? Have you transgressed
שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz or not? You didn't do the act of
שחיטה, shechitah, but you did the effect of שחיטה shechitah on the
child. אמר ליה. Amar leih. So he gave him another answer. He
said, look, it's a פסוק. pasuk. Don't try to get fancy on
me. מי קרינא ביה ויביאום לה'? Mi karina beih v'yevi'um l'Hashem? The
פסוק pasuk tells you don't shecht your קרבנות korbanos out of the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, rather bring them to God. Which means that
what? You're only חייב chayav in something that at this could have
been brought as a קרבן. korban. While it was a fetus, it
couldn't yet be brought as a קרבן, korban, so you get off
on a technicality. Okay, because it wasn't fit yet to be brought
as a קרבן. korban. Okay, and there's a normal phrase for that
which we're going to say in the לשון אחר. lashon acher. לישנא
אחרינא אמר ליה ראוי לפתח אהל מועד חייבין עליו בחוץ. Lishna acharina
amar leih ra'uy l'pesach ohel mo'ed chayavin alav bachutz. Only if it
was fit to be brought, this was not yet fit to be
brought. So again, it did not get to the heart of the
question, which is, does it go by the act of שחיטה shechitah
or the result of שחיטה? shechitah? It goes by a technicality. You
know, if not, it's not fit for אהל מועד, ohel moed, which
is like I told you, reminds me again of that story I
think I told you this one recently. You know that somebody comes
into ישיבה yeshiva and everybody's learning קידושין Kiddushin and he asks the
people like, okay, so can an androgynous marry himself? So everybody's like,
hey, no, is this a מעשה נסינה? maiseh nissina? Is this considered
an act? Is there a קבלה? kabbalah? And he says, of course
not, it's his sister. So
that's sort of what's happening here. By what? So is it the
מעשה שחיטה? maiseh shechitah? Is it the result of שחיטה? shechitah? It's
not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. rauy lepesach ohel moed. All right, moving
on. That was a fantastic question. All right, anyway, that obviously was
tied into the fact that they were separating the mother from the
child. That ends the discussion before, which was quite interesting and challenging.
So now we've had a משנה, mishna, think about where we are
in the משניות mishnayot and I'm telling you this because the next
משניות mishnayot are now going to sort of move in a different
direction. We opened with a משנה mishna about הכל ממירין, hakol memirin,
who are the people that can do תמורה? tmura? Then we spoke
about, it's actually, you know, very מסודר mesudar from, you know, מסכתא,
masechta, sometimes they start like off-topic and move around. Here it's like
really sort of starts from the beginning. Who can do תמורה? tmura?
What objects can you do it on? Like in terms of, you
know, one animal, sheep and goat versus goats versus cows, one to
many, parts of animals, fetuses and limbs, and that was our whole
discussion about the status of a fetus and תמורה tmura of a
fetus. So we've sort of laid out some of the basic parameters
about the object and the people. Now we're going to turn to
a series of משניות mishnayot that are more sort of grouped together
because of a similar structure, but sort of will move us away
from a direct discussion of תמורה. tmura. You'll take a look at
the beginning, you'll see at the end where this will sort of
connect to תמורה, tmura, but it's going to be after this a
series of משניות mishnayot that are not directly related. Let's take a
look. אין המדומה מדמע אלא לפי חשבון. Ein hameduma medameya ela lefi
cheshbon.
So דמוע dimua is when תרומה truma is mixed with חולין. chulin.
Okay, now, so מדומה meduma is when you have again that status
of תרומה truma mixed with חולין chulin and it's not בטל. batel.
For תרומה truma to be בטל batel it has to be a
hundred against one, not just sixty against one. Now you have one
unit of תרומה truma falls into, you know, ninety-nine or fifty, let's
make it easier, fifty units of חולין chulin and now it all
gets mixed up. Now you have one unit from that mixture fall
into another fifty units. How much תרומה truma fell into mixture number
two? So, you know, you could, logically it would be one-fiftieth of
a unit fell into mixture number two, or one-fifty-first, whatever, doesn't matter,
into mixture number two and therefore it's בטל batel because mixture number
two has two hundred and fifty, two thousand five hundred times as
much. But if you wanted to really be strict, you could say,
look, that one unit that you took from the first mixture was
all forbidden. It was all forbidden because it had one-fiftieth of תרומה,
truma, but it was all forbidden. We're going to treat it all
as תרומה truma and we're going to say one unit fell into
number two and number two is also forbidden. So the משנה mishna
says not that way. אין המדומה, Ein hameduma, something that is mixed,
is not מדמע, medameya, does not make the next sort of series
of mixture forbidden, אלא לפי חשבון, ela lefi cheshbon, except according to
the appropriate proportion. You don't treat it as all תרומה, truma, you
only treat it as a proportion and therefore you figure out the
math regarding the second mixture it falls into. ואין המחומץ מחמיץ אלא
לפי חשבון. V'ein hamuchmat machmitz ela lefi cheshbon. Something that is made
חמץ chametz is only also affects the next presumably the next mixture
or is determined based on proportion. We'll see what that means in
the גמרא, Gemara, but the basic point here is is that if
you have a mixture and normally the by percentage, by proportion, the
amount of what is forbidden would be forbidden, would be בטל, batel,
excuse me, it's a small quantifiable amount, but nevertheless it has the
effect of making the mixture חמץ, chametz, it's yeast that falls into
dough. Because of that impact that it can do on the mixture,
even if it's small in a quantifiable amount, it is not חמץ,
chametz, it is not בטל. batel. But that is only according to
appropriate proportion. We'll see what that means in the גמרא. Gemara. I'm
not going to explain it now. ואין המים שאובין פוסלים את המקוה
אלא לפי חשבון. V'ein hamayim she'uvin poslim et hamikveh ela lefi cheshbon.
If you have drawn water, drawn water invalidates a מקוה. mikveh. Three
לוג log of drawn water invalidates a מקוה mikveh if it's before
the מקוה mikveh is already full. Once you have forty סאה se'ah
it's not true, but before you have forty סאה se'ah three לוג
log of drawn water invalidates a מקוה. mikveh. And that's only according
to the appropriate proportion. Again, what that means exactly we'll talk about
in the גמרא. Gemara. ואין מי חטאת עושים מי חטאת. V'ein mei
chatat osim mei chatat. Now here's where, so in the first part
was like it has to be a certain
proportion. That's not directly related to תמורה. tmura. Here you're going to
see where it relates to the תמורה tmura concept.
חטאת chatat water cannot make other חטאת chatat water אלא אם נתן
אפר, ela im natan efer, only if you add the dust, meaning
let's say I went ahead or the ash. I mixed the ashes
with the water and I made my חטאת chatat water from פרה
אדומה. parah adumah. Can I take some of this mixture, which is
a mixture of the water and the ashes, put it into new
water and make the new water into פרה אדומה parah adumah water,
into חטאת chatat water? The answer is no. The way you do
it,
the recipe is ashes and water, not you take from the mixture
and you add to the water. So once you have this mixture,
you can't now make other water into מי חטאת. mei chatas. I
assume you can see where we're headed now with this more idea.
Okay, ואין בית הפרס עושים בית הפרס. ve'ein beis hapras osin beis
hapras. בית הפרס beis hapras is an area, a valley, whatever, a
field
that had a grave and the field was plowed over and therefore
somewhere in this field there are bits and pieces of a dead
body. In this type of a case, כהנים kohanim cannot walk anywhere
in the field. And let's say you had that field and it
was already plowed over and then they plowed from this field and
they continue and they plowed into the next field. So can one
בית הפרס beis hapras make another field into a בית הפרס? beis
hapras? And the answer is no. A בית הפרס beis hapras is
made by there being a grave and the field being plowed over,
not having an already plowed over field being plowed into the next
field. Okay, and so now you're seeing again the structure where we're
leading up to תמורה. tmurah.
Even if you have that status in A, you don't take something
from A and turn it into B. Okay, so you don't take
פרה אדומה, parah adumah, you know, אפר eifer מי חטאת mei chatas
and make something else מי חטאת. mei chatas. You need to actually
mix the water with the ashes. You don't take a בית הפרס
beis hapras and make the other thing בית הפרס, beis hapras, you
actually have to plow over the grave. And therefore, this leading up
to our case, ואין תרומה, ve'ein trumah, excuse me, one before our
case, ואין תרומה אחר תרומה. ve'ein trumah achar trumah. You can't do
תרומה trumah twice. If you took תרומה trumah from grain once and
then you tried to take תרומה trumah from grain a second time,
the second thing did not become תרומה, trumah, which is a little
different. It's doing the same thing to the first one as opposed
to doing it to the changed one. But anyway, ואין תמורה עושה
תמורה. ve'ein tmurah osah tmurah.
It's a nice תרומה עושה תרומה, trumah osah trumah, תמורה עושה תמורה.
tmurah osah tmurah. Okay, right. Anyway, and תמורה tmurah does not make
a תמורה tmurah and this is what it's doing here. So I
made, you know, I took my קרבן korban and I transferred it
and I tried to exchange it with A to B. B became
תמורה. tmurah. B cannot now make C into תמורה. tmurah. And that
is again structurally similar to a בית הפרס beis hapras can't make
another thing בית הפרס, beis hapras, which is maybe most similar to
the idea that mixing the אפר eifer with the פרה אדומה parah
adumah that turned it into מי חטאת, mei chatas, but that doesn't
make the next thing into מי חטאת. mei chatas. Okay, so last
במתניתין, bematnitin, ולא הולד עושה תמורה. velo havlad oseh tmurah.
Now we're,
and something that is born from תמורה tmurah that has derivative, excuse
me, born from a קרבן, korban, excuse me, not born from תמורה.
tmurah. You sanctified a קרבן korban like the whole discussion before about
the mother and the child. You sanctified the mother and now it
gave birth, so this child has derivative קדושה, kedushah, not the original
קדושה. kedushah. That cannot make a תמורה. tmurah. רבי יהודה אומר הולד
עושה תמורה. Rabbi Yehuda omer havlad oseh tmurah. Rabbi Yehuda says a
child can do תמורה tmurah once it's born and we quoted that
a lot yesterday. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him, הקדש
עושה תמורה ואין הולד עושה תמורה. hekdesh oseh tmurah ve'ein havlad oseh
tmurah. I'm sorry, only the thing you directly sanctified can make תמורה
tmurah but not the child cannot make תמורה. tmurah. And if you
look at the side, there's another גרסא girsa which says ולא תמורה
עושה תמורה. velo tmurah osah tmurah. And a תמורה tmurah cannot make
a תמורה, tmurah, which was not part of their debate, but it
shows that this is like a phrase that was said together. You
can't have תמורה tmurah do a תמורה tmurah and you can't have
a child do תמורה, tmurah, which basically means only the original thing.
And you understand the conceptual similarity. תמורה tmurah sanctity is derived from
the original one, right? When I sanctify animal A and then I
try to exchange it with B and B becomes קדוש, kadosh, B's
קדושה kedushah derived from A and B is a תמורה. tmurah. B
cannot now make C a תמורה. tmurah. In a similar way, although
I didn't do a prohibition in this case, but in a similar
way if I sanctify the mother and then it gives birth to
a child, the קדושה kedushah of the child is derivative from the
mother. And therefore, that's the point. תמורה tmurah can't make a תמורה
tmurah and a child can't make תמורה. tmurah. Only the thing you
originally sanctified can make the תמורה, tmurah, not the thing that is
derived from it. So although that is the reason it's in this
מסכת, masechet, since it's part of this bundle of teaching, you know,
only these things are according to proportion, only these things it's the
original not the derivative, and תמורה tmurah is part of this, therefore
it gets placed here and we will see we'll now going to
have after this a series of משניות mishnayot that have these sort
of thematic groupings that are not exactly talking about תמורה, tmurah, תמורה
tmurah is just one of them and sometimes not even. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. gemara. But now we certainly shift gears
from what we've been talking about in this מסכת. masechet. So מאן
תנא, man tana, who is the תנא tana that says first this
idea of מדומע, meduma, of a mixture of תרומה trumah and other
things? Who is the תנא tana that says that you go according
to proportions? אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן דלא כרבי
אליעזר. amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan dela keRabbi Eliezer.
It's not like Rabbi Eliezer. דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה,
mishnah, סאה של תרומה שנפלה לפחות ממאה חולין. se'ah shel trumah shenafelah
lefachot mimayah chulin. A סאה se'ah of תרומה, trumah, unit of תרומה
trumah that fell into less than a hundred. A hundred it would
be בטל, batel, it fell into less than a hundred.
So then what happens? ונדמעו, venidme'u, it all became דמוע, dimu'a, it
all became a mixture of תרומה trumah and חולין chulin which is
forbidden. ונפל מן המדומע למקום אחר. venafal min hameduma lemakom acher. And
it fell from this mixture, let's say it's one in fifty, the
example I gave you, and then one unit from mixture A fell
into חולין chulin B. רבי אליעזר אומר מדמע כתרומה. Rabbi Eliezer omer
medame'a k'trumah. That one unit is considered all תרומה, trumah, כתרומה ודאי,
k'trumah vadai, that it's all. is considered all תרומה, terumah, we're going
to be strict and therefore we're going to say that the other
one only had 50, 50 against 1, it’s not בטל, batel, and
the whole second and whole B is all forbidden. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim
omrim and the sages say, or if you look at the parentheses
that's maybe a explanation of it but it isn't in the משנה,
mishnah, שאני אומר סאה שנפלה היא שעלתה, she’ani omer se’ah shenaphalah hi
she’altah, that I'll be strict and assume the exact same unit that
went in that fell in was the exact same unit that fell
into the next one. That might be the conceptual explanation. There's another
conceptual explanation, you would just say since the mixture is all forbidden
by treating it all forbidden as a mixture, we mean we're treating
it all as תרומה. terumah. נפקא מינה Naphka mina if two fell
in. Right, exactly. What if you had that two fell in would
be a very good נפקא מינה. naphka mina. Yes.
The
it being forbidden does not make it תרומה. terumah.
Right. So it becomes forbidden, it becomes forbidden like תרומה. terumah. Now
I should say that by normal הלכות כשרות hilchos kashrus we have
a principle of טעם כעיקר, ta’am k’ikar, which is like you know
if a little bit of חזיר chazir falls into a pot and
it can be tasted, the whole pot is forbidden. And there is
a position of the ראש Rosh that says the nature of טעם
כעיקר ta’am k’ikar is that since I can taste חזיר chazir in
every little drop of soup, so every drop of soup is considered
to be 100% חזיר. chazir. That normally is rejected, normally we say
like this, it's no, it means the חזיר chazir is still there
but only proportional to its only based on its exact proportional amount.
There is however a rabbinic concept not based on the טעם כעיקר
ta’am k’ikar that's תורה Torah based, but a rabbinic concept called חתיכה
נעשית נבלה, chatichah na’aseis neveilah, which means it's the whole piece becomes
like a נבלה, neveilah, becomes like intrinsically forbidden, which is essentially saying
the same thing except saying it on a rabbinic level. So you're
right, you could say it's forbidden because of the איסור issur that's
there but it's not איסור issur per se. But it seems that
Rabbi Eliezer is taking the next step, which you actually do find
sometimes by possibly it's you know it's based on a lot of
debates of ראשונים, rishonim, but there are positions like that when something
can be tasted. Okay, here it can't be tasted, it's all מין
במינו min b’mino number one, it's all grain in grain, number two
it's less than one in sixtieth, it's one in a hundred, but
nevertheless you do sometimes have similar types of ideas that at least
at a rabbinic level we will say it all becomes as if
it is the forbidden thing itself.
So this would affect the punishment if someone receives for eating the
forbidden?
Well, that depends if he's saying this biblically or rabbinically, presumably he's
saying this rabbinically, not biblically. Okay, so now the גמרא, Gemara, okay,
so that's his position. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim and the sages say
אינה מדמעת אלא לפי חשבון שבה. einah medama’as ela l’phi cheshbon shebah.
No, it's only according to its proportion. So actually the גמרא Gemara
is not just in a way telling you it's not Rabbi Eliezer,
it's also explaining to you with a משנה mishnah and showing you
how this exact phrase is expressed more fully and fleshed out in
this משנה mishnah in תרומה. terumah. Okay, so that's the debate of
חכמים Chachamim and Rabbi Eliezer and this משנה mishnah is assuming חכמים.
Chachamim. It's only according to its proportion in the mixture. ואינה מחמצת
מחמץ אלא לפי חשבון. V’einah mechamezes mechamez ela l’phi cheshbon. If it's
something that causes חמץ, chametz, again which prevents ביטול, bitul, it's only
according to the proportion. So let's see what this means. אמר רבי
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan: מתניתין דלא
כרבי אליעזר. matnisin d’lo k’Rabbi Eliezer. Once again it's not like Rabbi
Eliezer. דתנן במתניתין: D’tenan b’matnisin: שאור של חולין ושל תרומה שנפלו לתוך
העיסה. se’or shel chullin v’shel terumah shenaphalu l’soch ha’issah. You have yeast,
שאור se’or sourdough, but we'll call it yeast, of חולין chullin of
normal dough and תרומה terumah that both fell into dough. So you've
got dough, you've got a little bit of yeast, the yeast is
half made up of חולין chullin and half made up of תרומה.
terumah. Now only this amount of yeast will cause this dough to
ferment. So if you ask yourself, did the תרומה terumah cause it
to ferment? Not by itself, only in conjunction with the חולין. chullin.
So the תרומה terumah is not doing it by itself, it's only
doing it together with the חולין. chullin. Is there enough תרומה terumah
to create a problem? No, we're assuming it's less than one in
a hundred. Less than one in a hundred it would be בטל,
batel, but the thing that might make it not בטל batel is
that it had an impact on the dough, it made the dough
ferment, it was מחמיץ. machmitz. That would prevent ביטול, bitul, but it
didn't do it by itself, it only did it in conjunction with
the חולין chullin yeast. So what's the הלכה? halacha? ושל שנפלו לתוך
העיסה ולא בזה כדי להחמיץ ולא בזה כדי להחמיץ, v’shel shenaphalu l’soch
ha’issah v’lo b’zeh k’dei l’hachmitz v’lo b’zeh k’dei l’hachmitz, each one of
the yeasts could not sufficiently cause it
to ferment, ונתערבו והחמיצו v’nis’arvu v’hechmisu and they work together to create
to make it ferment and to make it into you know to
make it חמץ. chametz. Rabbi Eliezer אומר: omer: אחר אחרון אני בא.
achar acharon ani ba. The one that came last, meaning the first
one didn't have any effect if they fell in separately, sequentially. But
the second yeast is the one that tipped the scales, caused the
fermenting to take place. So therefore the second one will be considered
if that was תרומה terumah then it's all forbidden. Now what if
you didn't have it sequentially? What if you had it at the
same time? So רש"י Rashi quotes a whole discussion in another גמרא
Gemara where he says the conclusion of that גמרא Gemara is that
even at the same time that would be enough to create a
problem as long as it wasn't first. Okay, if it was first
then you say it didn't have any effect when it fell in.
But if it fell in together with the חולין chullin yeast or
after the חולין chullin yeast, then it's considered to not be בטל
batel to have had its impact on the yeast. That's what Rabbi
Eliezer says, on the dough. That's what Rabbi Eliezer says. וחכמים אומרים:
Vachachamim omrim: בין שנפל בתחילה בין שנפל בסוף, bein shenaphal b’techilah bein
shenaphal b’soph, I don't care if it fell at the beginning or
the end, לעולם אינו אוסר עד שיהא בו כדי להחמיץ. l’olam eino
oser ad sheyehei bo k’dei l’hachmitz. It needs to have enough enough
power to ferment by itself, which is some, which is sometimes rephrased
as זה וזה גורם. ze v'ze gorem. If you have two things,
each one which were necessary, not sufficient by themselves, necessary to have
an impact, is it, does it create a problem if, you know,
one of them was a forbidden thing? So, you know, or does
it have to do it by itself? So here, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer would say זה וזה גורם ze v'ze gorem is אסור, assur,
as long, but not always, because he would admit that if the
yeast fell in first it would be okay. But there are cases
where even though it's working in conjunction, it's still a problem. וחכמים
Vachachamim say זה וזה גורם ze v'ze gorem מותר. mutar. No, since
it couldn't do it by itself, it's not a problem. So what
does that mean in the משנה? mishna?
One minute, what does that mean in the משנה? mishna? So אינה
מחומצת מחמץ אלא לפי חשבון eina mechumetzet mechometz ela lefi cheshbon does
not mean the same thing as before. It's not talking about falling
into pile A and from pile A into pile B. It means
that you have a yeast mixture, and this yeast mixture falls into
dough. Okay, we only consider whether it makes the dough forbidden based
on the amount of תרומה terumah in it. And since the amount
of תרומה terumah in the yeast mixture is insufficient to have that
impact, it is not a problem. So לפי חשבון lefi cheshbon means
you look at the yeast, you figure out how much of that
yeast is
תרומה, terumah, and only if the תרומה terumah yeast will have the
impact is it a problem. If it needs to use the חולין
chulin yeast together with it, you're okay.
Yeah, this זה וזה גורם ze v'ze gorem unless different principles might
be translated to, let's say, you and I, you know, carrying something
on שבת. Shabbat.
So that's שנים שעשו. shnayim she'asu.
That's not זה וזה גורם.
ze
v'ze gorem.
I mean, both cause it to be moved
out of the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Yes, there's similarities, but it's
not the same. That's when two people are doing a forbidden act,
can you attribute the act to, you know, one of them or
the fact that both of them are doing it, neither can be
held responsible? But that's about liability and responsibility. It's not about sort
of whether it made an impact on the thing and whether you
see its effect on the thing that it was resulting. Okay, so
there's obviously parallels there, but that's much more about personal liability, that's
the case of שנים שעשו. shnayim she'asu. That's not exactly the same
as
זה וזה גורם. ze v'ze gorem. I don't know, but they're similar,
I mean, you know, they're analogous, but they're not the same issue.
Okay, so that's what it means לפי חשבון. lefi cheshbon. You look
at how much, I, by the way, read it like תוספות. Tosafot.
רש"י Rashi reads it in a more complicated way. תוספות Tosafot is
more straightforward. So according to that, the point is you look at
the amount of yeast that's תרומה, terumah, that's what matters. You don't
do the whole thing as forbidden.
Nothing to do with פסח Pesach then?
No, nothing, it's all about ביטול. bitul. Okay, that one of the
things that prevents ביטול bitul is that it ferments, it causes fermentation.
Okay, now, ואין המים שאובים פוסלים את המקוה. ve'ein hamayim she'uvim poslim
et hamikvah. Drawn water, three לוג log of drawn water. By the
way, if you want to know how much a לוג log is,
the amount of wine we have
for קידוש Kiddush is a רביעית. revi'it. A רביעית revi'it is a
רביעית revi'it of a לוג. log. You normally assume that's about three
and a half ounces is how much you need for קידוש. Kiddush.
So you multiply that by four, that's what is that, 14 ounces?
That's a לוג. log. So three לוג log is how much drawn
water פוסל possel a מקוה, mikvah, which is 30, 52 ounces? What?
How much is that?
52? No, I'm sorry, 42. I did my math bad. What, five
cups? Yeah, five. A normal cup is what, like eight ounces? Okay,
so not this, right? This is an eight ounce?
That's probably an eight ounce.
This
is a 12. Yeah, eight ounces are the more sort of small
plastic. Okay, so anyway, so about, okay, so a little bit more
than three of these. If you have that falling into a מקוה,
mikvah, drawn water, meaning not rainwater, falling into a מקוה mikvah before
the מקוה mikvah is full, it invalidates. And let me just say
one thing about this because, you know, when you go to the
מקוה, mikvah, which, you know, when you go to the מקוה, mikvah,
men do it some rare times. Anyway, it's not like you're actually
being טובל tovel in rainwater. What do you do? What you do
is you collect rainwater in a separate בור, bor, in a separate
like, you know, pit or whatever, I mean with cement, anyway, you
collect that rainwater. Then that's a full מקוה. mikvah. Once you have
a full מקוה, mikvah, you can't invalidate. No matter how much other
water you put in. So what you do is you put in
in a separate place where you actually do the טבילה, tevilah, you
actually run, you know,
you know with the pipe or whatever, clean water from the pipes,
okay, and you put that in the separate pit and they connect
with a tiny little opening. So because they connect, it's halachically considered
one מקוה. mikvah. Because this מקוה mikvah was כשר kasher first, no
matter how much of the drawn water you're adding to it, because
conceptually you're adding to it because they're connected now, you can't invalidate.
Then when you want to כשר kasher the מקוה, mikvah, you clean
the whole thing out, you know, not כשר, kasher, excuse me, when
you want to like clean the מקוה, mikvah, but you remove all
the water, you clean it out, you pour in new water and
again this one with the 40 סאה, se'ah, which is the rainwater,
is okay because
it remained rainwater and never got less. Now there is a question
about that though, are you concerned about eventual transference of how much,
whatever, I don't want to get into that. Anyway, that's, but if
the drawn water fell in before the 40 סאה, se'ah, it invalidates.
And now we're going to say something about לפי חשבון, lefi cheshbon,
figuring out what exactly that means. I would say that it's interesting
because I would have imagined what that means is is that let's
say you have this מקווה mikvah that had I don't know ten
סאה se'ah and now three לוג log of drawn water fell in
and it's now a פסול pasul מקווה. mikvah. And let's say some
of that water now if you pulled it, you know, if you
used a cup and removed it and put it into another מקווה,
mikvah, then that's been made into drawn water. But let's say you
didn't. Let's say somehow it just, I don't know, by itself overflowed
and ran into another מקווה. mikvah. Okay, so then it's similar to
the question before about the תרומה, terumah, right? How much drawn water
fell into the other מקווה? mikvah? I would say oh, only the
amount of proportion. You don't treat it all as drawn water. That's
what I would have imagined we're talking about. The גמרא Gemara interprets
it in a different way. We will see how the גמרא Gemara
understands what this לפי חשבון lefi cheshbon means. Yes.
Maybe this is too much to determine right now, but the Lubavitchers
have a position about where the actual מקווה mikvah has to be
relative to where...
Yeah, there's a question about side by side, top and bottom. Yeah,
we're not getting into that. Okay, so let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so it's all by drawn water invalidating the
מקווה, mikvah, but presumably because the reason the גמרא Gemara reads it
not the way I did is it sounds like we're talking about
the first invalidation. Meaning the way I read it is it invalidated
the first מקווה, mikvah, what do you, you know, it's only proportional
for the second מקווה. mikvah. But the פשט pshat but the language
says that when it invalidates the מקווה mikvah the first time or
the only time, that's according to the proportion. So what does that
mean? So מאן תנא, man tanna, who is this? אמר רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov היא. hi. It's
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. דתנן, de-tnan, we learned
in a משנה, Mishnah, actually it's דתניא, de-tanya, ברייתא, Baraita, תוספתא Tosefta
in מקואות. Mikvaot. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
omer, מקווה שיש בו עשרים ואחת סאה מי גשמים, mikvah she-yesh bo
esrim ve-achat se'ah mei geshamim, there were 22 סאה se'ah of rainwater.
21. 21, excuse me, 21 סאה, se'ah, more than the majority, right?
40 is the total amount that you need. ממלא בכתף תשעה
עשר סאה, memaleh be-katef tish'ah asar se'ah, you can fill with the
shoulder, meaning you can like
draw
water, draw buckets of water, 19. So this is the remainder of
what you need, but it's the minority, the 19 סאה. se'ah. ופוטקן
למקווה u-potkan la-mikvah והן טהורים. ve-hen tehorim. And you can pour them
into the מקווה mikvah and the מקווה mikvah is okay. Now it
doesn't mean directly, but what it means is like you pour it
down a pipe into the מקווה. mikvah. Why? שהרובה מטהרת ברביעית ובהמשכה,
she-ha-rubah metaheret bi-revi'it u-ve-hamshachah,
because drawn water can become kosher if it is made kosher through
majority and being drawn, which means and being like run, drawn, not
drawn water, gotta have another word, like המשיך hamshich means to anyway
running on the ground. Okay, meaning the following: that although three לוג
log invalidates the מקווה, mikvah, according to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov, there's a way you can get around that. As
long as the amount of drawn water is the minority, meaning the
מקווה mikvah started with 21 kosher סאה, se'ah, right? And it's only
19 סאה se'ah or less. And what you do is you don't
pour the water directly into the מקווה. mikvah. You have it, you
pour it on the ground and it runs into the מקווה. mikvah.
Then it's pseudo-natural. Okay, you know, it makes it a little more
natural. It's not so much a
manufactured, what's the better word, what are you talking about something that
you like construct
by human
hands? Not manufactured, I think, thank you, that's the word. Okay, yeah,
but manufactured is closer to the point. Right, part of the whole
point of drawing is a question about how process, well I think
manufactured, question is why is drawn water a problem? Is it like
the water is פסול, pasul, there's like some פסול psul in the
water, you know? Or is it that by drawing water it makes
the מקווה mikvah not natural? By having the מקווה mikvah constructed through
human effort, the first 40 סאה se'ah which define its identity, then
it makes it a non-natural מקווה. mikvah. So it seems like that's
part of the idea here. And therefore what he's saying is as
long as the majority was kosher and as long as it didn't
go directly from you into the מקווה, mikvah, it ran on the
ground so it's a little bit more natural when it gets formed,
it's coming from the ground, not from you, that's okay. Okay, and
that's what he would say, which by the way would be a
nice קולא kullah for in all places because they get a lot
of rainwater, but if you're allowed to start by the majority and
then fill it up with drawn water in this way, that's an
idea.
You fill the 100, this will be fine, right?
Once the first 21 were okay, then you're fine.
Now where does drawn water come from?
Well, it comes from the pipes, it might come from the sea,
it might... but eventually it was natural at one point, but as
soon as you make it under human control, it loses its status
to be able to be used as a מקווה. mikvah. There's even
a discussion about what happens if the rainwater falls into a vessel
and you never touched it, but it fell into vessels on your
roof and then the vessels broke and ran into a מקווה. mikvah.
Is the fact that they were in a vessel somehow make it
more like human as opposed to falling natural?
Rainwater is in the, the rainwater's anyway in a vessel.
No, it's collected through pipes. Okay, pipes are different because the pipes
don't have a receptacle, they run straight through pipes, but because there's
no receptacle, they're not considered a vessel. That's how it works. Also
it's very important that the pipes are not מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah.
There's a lot of הלכה halachah about this.
Pipe is a receptacle.
No, a receptacle... receptacle halakhically means that there, means that it has
a bottom. Okay? Here, it never has a bottom, it just goes
straight through the pipes into, into the pit. So then the pit's
the bottom. No, the pit is in the ground, it isn't the
bottom of the pipe. Okay? A receptacle that makes something more sort
of under human control, you know, is something that holds the water,
you know, separate from the, you know, from its natural world, you
know. Here, the pipe doesn't hold it and the pit is a
pit in the ground. All right, so anyway, don't make it terrible,
רבקה, Rivka, I don't want to pass our מקואות. mikvahs. All right,
anyway, all right, so anyway, that's his position. So what does it
mean לפי חשבון? lefi cheshbon? It means you don't automatically say, "Oh
God, drawn water, the מקווה's mikvah פסול." pasul. No, it depends on
the numbers. It depends if you started with 21 and in the
circumstance where it was ran on the ground and didn't go straight
in, it only is based on if it's the numbers based on
the majority, if it's in the minority, if it's 19 סאה se'ah
or less, then you're okay. Okay, so that's a very different read
of לפי חשבון, lefi cheshbon, but it means don't automatically invalidate it,
you have to look at the proportion. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, the גמרא Gemara says מכלל דרבנן סברי, mikhlal
de-rabbanan savri,
first read this גמרא Gemara like רש"י Rashi and then I'll tell
you how תוספות Tosafot reads this. That would suggest that the Rabbis
hold דרביה והמשכה לא, darbiya ve-hamshacha lo, that that would not work
if you drew it and if you ran it on the water
and it was only and it was where the majority was already
in the מקווה, mikvah, because it sounds like our משנה Mishnah is
being lenient, right? The simple sense of our משנה Mishnah is don't
invalidate it automatically, it depends on the proportions and the numbers. So
it sounds like there's another position out there by the Rabbis that
would say that this case would be invalid. But אהא כי אתא
רבין, a-ha ki ata Ravin,
but how about when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, he said in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, שהוא וששיכו כולו טהור, she-hu ve-she-shichu kulo tahor,
that
actually the opposing position is more lenient. The opposing position says that
even if you did this to all of the water, it's okay.
Okay? So therefore you can't
say, "Oh, he's being lenient, he says you can do this on
19 סאה, se'ah, the minority of the water," because he's actually not
being lenient, there's actually a more lenient position out there that says
that you can do it on all the water and the simple
read of our משנה Mishnah is that the positions in the משנה
Mishnah are the lenient ones. So the גמרא Gemara says, "All right,
so מני, mani, so according to you, לא רבנן ולא רבי אליעזר.
lo Rabbanan ve-lo Rabbi Eliezer. It's not the Rabbis and it's not
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's only
the minority and you're implying, you're suggesting that the Rabbis are more
strict, but we actually know that the Rabbis are more lenient. So
that can't be right. It can't be that the משנה Mishnah is
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer because that would imply that the Rabbis are
more strict." אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, לפי חשבון כלים. lefi
cheshbon kelim. What it says according to the
number, what it means is it depends on the number of vessels.
What does this mean? יוסף בן חוני, Yosef ben Choni, it's יוסף
בן חוני. Yosef ben Choni. דתניא, De-tanya, שלשה לוגין מים שאובים שנפלו
למים, shelosha lugin mayim she-uvim she-naflu le-mayim, so if you have these
three לוג log that fell into the water, בשנים ובשלשה כלים ואפילו
בארבעה ובחמשה כלים פוסלים את המקווה. bi-shnayim u-vi-shelosha kelim ve-afillu be-arba ve-chamisha
kelim poslim et ha-mikvah. No matter how many times, how many ways
that three לוג log was distributed, if it was one vessel, two
vessels, three vessels, five vessels, ten vessels, it doesn't matter. The end
of the day, three לוג log fell into the מקווה mikvah before
it was full, the מקווה mikvah is invalid. That's what the חכמים
Chachamim say. יוסף בן חוני אומר, Yosef ben Choni omer, יוסף בן
חוני Yosef ben Choni
disagrees. He says no. בשנים ובשלשה כלים פוסל את המקווה, bi-shnayim u-vi-shelosha
kelim posel et ha-mikvah, two or three vessels it will invalidate the
מקווה, mikvah, בארבעה ובחמשה אין פוסל את המקווה, be-arba ve-chamisha ein posel
et ha-mikvah, four or five not, and obviously more. Now why should
it matter? At the end of the day, three לוג log fell
into the מקווה. mikvah. So again, what I believe his position is,
is that it's not about the water per se being invalid, but
that when it's in, but you have made the מקווה mikvah manufactured.
So if each time you pour water in a מקווה mikvah it's
a few drops, it's less than a לוג, log, so it's not
like you've done any meaningful act to the מקווה. mikvah. In order
for you to have done a meaningful act, each act has to
have put in at least a לוג log of water. So if
you do two or three vessels, so each act equally distributed, each
act was at least a לוג log of water, then you have
done these three acts and it's had an impact and it's been
a total of three לוג log and therefore it's created into a
manufactured מקווה. mikvah. But if each act is less than that, then
it's not enough to have actually invalidated the מקווה. mikvah. Okay, no,
you did not do any significant type of act. That's the position.
One minute. So לפי חשבון שבה lefi cheshbon she-ba means don't automatically
say that, "Oh my God, any three לוג log of water invalidates."
No, you have to figure out the number, depending on how many
different vessels it was distributed among, maybe it did invalidate, maybe it
did not. Seth, you had a question?
Yes, so they're assuming that כלים kelim are a standardized measurement here?
Yeah, no, not clearly, it does seem to be assuming, although it's
not spelled out in this משנה. Mishnah. There is some discussion. I
was assuming that what he says that he is talking about equal
distribution, because the question would be according to him, let's say you
had two vessels, one had 2.9 לוג log and the other had
0.1 לוג. log. So according to the way I'm describing it, that
each act has to be significant, that would be no good, you
would need at least one לוג log per act and if some,
yeah, that is somewhat debated. So I was making that assumption, it
doesn't have to, it's not necessarily the case. Now I did want
to say another thing about this large תוספות, Tosafot, because the way
רש"י Rashi read the גמרא, Gemara,
there was a position of the רבנן Rabbanan that says you could
do המשכה hamshacha for the entire מקווה. mikvah. Now that would be...
be an amazing קולא. Kula. That would mean that even if you
can't get rainwater as long as you do המשכה Hamshacha for the
entire מקוה, Mikvah, right? המשכה Hamshacha means you pour it on the
ground and you let it run, it would be okay. And תוספות
Tosfos and that was a major major discussion in ראשונים. Rishonim. You
have huge תשובות Tshuvos and writings of the ראשונים Rishonim about whether
המשכה Hamshacha works for the entire מקוה Mikvah or only for the
minority of it. So even according to רש"י Rashi there would be
a question about how we פוסקן posken and what's indicated by other
משניות, Mishnayos, whether you can do המשכה Hamshacha for the majority only
or a minority. But I should also say that תוספות Tosfos basically
reads the גמרא, Gemara, he so much thinks that the idea you
could do המשכה Hamshacha for all of this goes against so much
of everything else we see about מקואות Mikvaos that he even reads
this גמרא Gemara that we have in a different way that
it's a harder read in the גמרא Gemara and it has to
do also with I think a slightly different גרסא. girsa. But anyway,
but the important point is is that there's a question about what
you know how to read and what the גרסא girsa of our
גמרא Gemara is, whether you even entertain the possibility that anybody holds
that the majority of it is that you can do it on
all of it. And number two, whether even if you do, whether
we פוסקן posken that way or not. I think he says if
you want the quick answer, I think he says
oh, that the opinion that says you can do המשכה Hamshacha on
all of it is only if you also have 40 סאה se'ah
of rainwater. You didn't have to start with 40 סאה se'ah of
rainwater, then everybody agrees you can't פוסל, posel, but you need to
have 40 סאה se'ah of rainwater somewhere in the mixture. Okay, so
there are ways of limiting this rule that you can do המשכה
Hamshacha on all of it. If you start with 40 סאה se'ah
of rainwater you can add as much שאובים she'uvim as you want.
But there are those that are according to everybody, right? Yes. But
there's those that so much don't like it הלכתית, halachically, meaning not
because they don't like the פסק, psak, but they feel it goes
so much against all other sources that even this line that says
you could do המשכה Hamshacha on all of it, they'll say only
means that there's also 40 סאה se'ah of rainwater mixed in. It
don't have to be before you meaning they fall in the- no,
even afterwards. Therefore it would completely be okay, but at least at
the end there's also 40 סאה se'ah of rainwater. Anyway, the important
point is is that there is a major debate in the ראשונים
Rishonim about how we פוסקן posken about this and there was really
serious questions because there were places that they couldn't get rainwater and
they didn't have מים חיים mayim chayim like well water or whatever
to use either and there was a real question of can you
do המשכה בכולה? Hamshacha bekula? Okay, and that was and it really
does depend on how you read this גמרא Gemara and then how
you
פוסקן.
posken. Yes. What? How much is the טהרה? tahara?
How much is the טהרה? tahara? What do you mean? How much
water do you need for a מקוה? Mikvah?
How much is the- oh,
for a מקוה Mikvah how much water do you need? So you
need 40 סאה se'ah which is I don't know exactly how to
do the math, but it's about a bathtub full of water. Okay?
It's enough water for a human to fully immerse in. So about
a bathtub of water. Yes.
So the מסכת מקואות Masechet Mikvaos is in סדר טהרות Seder Taharos
where there's no גמרא. Gemara.
Yeah, we're not going to do it.
Yeah, I know.
But there's no גמרא, Gemara, so how do we go through a
הלכתי halachic process?
Okay, so that's a very good question because of גמרות Gemaras like
this. Because number one, there
are the ראשונים Rishonim that just work on it and analyze the
משניות Mishnayos on themselves. There's a רמב"ם Rambam on the משנה, Mishna,
there's ר"ש, Rash, which is the ר"ש משאנץ, Rash mi-Shantz, which is
one of the תלמידי talmidei of the ר"י Ri of תוספות, Tosfos,
and then there's the ראב"ד Ra'avad who wrote a פירוש peirush on
משניות. Mishnayos. But even there you could say what material do they
have to work with? Right. So they use תוספתא Tosefta and so
on. But when there's ירושלמי Yerushalmi available they use ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, but
there's no ירושלמי Yerushalmi on טהרות. Taharos. But what they wind up
using is when the גמרות, Gemaras, בבלי Bavli and ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, quote
these משניות Mishnayos indirectly in the middle of other discussions. And then
they really rely very, very heavily on this. Okay? Which is why
if you just had this גמרא Gemara you would say, oh look,
you can do המשכה Hamshacha on all of it. But then if
you try to reconcile it with all the משניות, Mishnayos, which is
what תוספות Tosfos does, it doesn't fit easily with a lot of
the משניות Mishnayos over there in טהרות, Taharos, which leads for תוספות
Tosfos to limit the implications of this line that you can do
המשכה Hamshacha on all of it. But it's a combination of knowing
the משניות Mishnayos and תוספתא Tosefta and knowing when the גמרא Gemara
quotes these related sources.
Okay. By the way, just one more point about this last thing
about two or three vessels. If you- because I mentioned the ראב"ד,
Ra'avad, if you look at תוספות יום טוב Tosfos Yom Tov and
you go down three lines where there's a little ל"ח lamed-chet in
brackets, he says ופסק הרב אברהם בר
דוד.
u-pasak ha-Rav Avraham
bar David. Anybody know who רב אברהם בר דוד Rav Avraham bar
David is? The ראב"ד, Ra'avad, אברהם בן דוד, Avraham ben David, Frank.
So there are a few תוספות יום טוב Tosfos Yom Tov that
relate to the ראב"ד. Ra'avad. ראב"ד Ra'avad wrote a lot of commentaries
on these more obscure things. He wrote a commentary on the ספרא,
Sifra, although I'm trying to remember if that's attributed to the ראב"ד
Ra'avad or actually the ראב"ד, Ra'avad, I think it is actually the
ראב"ד, Ra'avad, and he wrote a- which so when the ספרא Sifra
is the פירוש peirush on is the תנאים Tannaim on ויקרא, Vayikra,
which a lot of times deals with Tannaitic material that relate to
these types of things. Also he wrote a commentary on the משנה,
Mishna, he wrote separate little compendiums of
הלכה. halacha. Most people know the ראב"ד Ra'avad as the one who
does the critique on the רמב"ם, Rambam, but his... His real work
in terms of a מחדש Mechadesh and a פוסק Posek and whatever
was well before the רמב"ם Rambam ever came onto the scene, and
the ראשונים Rishonim know it, they're constantly quoting. Anyway. What? He lived
12th century.
Let me see these תוספות. Tosafos.
12th to 13th century. Okay. So anyway, there's a פסוק Pasuk דאף
יוסף בן חוני. D'af Yosef ben Choni. Okay, so he actually rules
leniently, which is important. Okay, which means that לפיכך נראה, L'fikach nireh,
here's a practical
implication, תשאוב את המקוה לנקותו, Tish'ov et hamikveh l'nakoto, when you empty
out the מקוה Mikveh to clean it, שנותנים אותן מים שבתוכו ובאים
מים אחרים תחתיהן, Shenotnim otan mayim shebetocho uba'im mayim acheirim tachtehen, okay,
that you remove all the water, you clean it out and then
other water takes the place, אין לחוש אפילו נשאר קצת מן הראשונים
במקוה דאף על גב שנפל מן הדלי לתוכו. Ein lachosh afilu nish'ar
k'tzat min harishonim bamikveh, d'af al gav shenafal min hadli letocho. So
it sounds like what's happening is not like you're doing this idea
of you're running new water and you're connecting it through a little
hole, you're actually getting new rainwater. So you clean out the old
one, and then what happens though, as you're cleaning it out and
removing it, you're drawing it with a vessel, and some splashes over.
So even when you clean it, there's a little water left on
the floor. Now that little water left on the floor might have
come from your bucket back on the floor, and it might be
שלשה לוגין. Shlosha lugin. And now who cares how much new rainwater
you get in? You start, you have שלשה לוגין Shlosha lugin in
here. Says don't worry about it. Why? דהוו לשם יותר מג' לוגין
מים שאפילו הכי אין לחוש דמסתמא לא נפלו ג' לוגין משלשה כלים,
D'havu l'sham yoter migimel lugin mayim she'afilu hachi ein lachosh, d'misama lo
naflu gimel lugin mishlosha keilim, because a little bit fell from each
vessel, but it's not that you had a לוג Log falling from
each vessel, tiny little drops. So even though they collect to שלשה
לוגין, Shlosha lugin, if we פוסקן Pasken like this idea that it
has to be שלשה לוגין Shlosha lugin from three vessels, you're okay.
ויש מחמירים, V'yeish machmirim, and some are מחמיר Machmir and they make
a little hole in the bucket, so even when you draw the
water, it's not considered really drawn water because the bucket has a
hole. That slows up the process a little bit, one could imagine.
Anyway, so here you have two very important halachic questions about can
you do המשכה Hamshacha with all the water, and whether if you
have מים שאובים, Mayim She'uvim, is it only when it's divided between
three or fewer vessels. Okay, now we get on to the next
part of the משנה, Mishnah, back to the גמרא. Gemara. ומי חטאת
עושים מי חטאת. V'amei chatas osim amei chatas. If you have one
mixture of מי חטאת, Mei Chatas, it's, this is where it's more
similar structurally to תמורה, Temurah, it doesn't make the other thing into
מי חטאת. Mei Chatas. מי חטאת Mei Chatas is only ashes and
water, not מי חטאת Mei Chatas water added to other water. Okay.
ומי חטאת נעשו מי חטאת. V'amei chatas na'asu mei chatas. מאן תנא,
Man tanna, who is this? אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן דלא כרבי שמעון. Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan,
d'lo k'Rabbi Shimon. It's not רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דתניא, D'tanya, we
taught in the ברייתא, Braisa, תוספתא Tosefta in פרה, Parah, הקדים עפר
למים פסול. Hikdim afar l'mayim pasul. If you first have the ashes
and then the water, it's invalid. Actually, this is not ashes, this
is dirt. This is talking about a similar mixture except not of
אפר Eifer and water, but of עפר Afar and water, which is
for the סוטה. Sotah. When you take from the ground of the
temple, of the משכן, Mishkan, and you mix it with the water.
So let's say you had the dirt first and then the water,
that's invalid. רבי שמעון מכשיר. Rabbi Shimon machshir. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says it's okay. מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Shimon? What's
the reasoning? כתיב, K'siv, ולקחו לטמא מעפר שריפת החטאת. V'lakchu latamei mei'afar
sreifas hachatas. This is by the ashes of the פרה אדומה. Parah
Adumah. You shall take from the ashes, although here it doesn't say
אפר, Eifer, it says עפר, Afar, dirt, so that's a funny word
to be using here. ונתן עליו מים חיים. V'natan alav mayim chayim.
And you put on it water. ותניא, V'tanya, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
אומר, Omer, וכי עפר הוא? V'chi afar hu? Is that really dirt
for the פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah? ולא אפר הוא? V'lo eifer hu?
It's ashes. שינה כתוב ממשמעו. Shina kasuv mimashmao.
So why does it say dirt when it really means to say
ashes? לדון ממנו גזירה שוה Ladon mimenu gezeira shava in order to
connect it, to make a גזירה שוה Gezeira shava to connect it
to the סוטה Sotah case. נאמר כאן עפר, Ne'emar kan afar, here
it says dirt, ונאמר להלן עפר, V'ne'emar lehalan afar, by סוטה. Sotah.
מה להלן עפר על גבי מים אף כאן עפר על גבי מים.
Mah lehalan afar al gabei mayim, af kan afar al gabei mayim.
Now, the same way by the סוטה, Sotah, the ideal way is
first water and then dirt, because that's what it says in the
פסוק. Pasuk. It says that you know, take the water, then it
says and you take from the dirt and you put it into
the water. So for the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, the best way
is first the water and then the ashes. That I'm not debating,
that that's the best way, first the water and then the ashes.
But, ומה כאן הקדים עפר למים כשר, U'mah kan hikdim afar l'mayim
kasher, by the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, ashes can come first, אף
כאן הקדים עפר למים כשר, Af kan hikdim afar l'mayim kasher, even
by the סוטה, Sotah, the dirt can come first. Now how do
I know that? How do I know the ashes can come first
from
the פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah? He takes it for granted, but how
does he know that? והכא מנלן? V'hacha minalan? How do we know
it here by the פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah? תרי קראי כתיבי. Trei
krayi ksivi. Two verses are written.
ונתן עליו. V'natan alav. Right? The simple read of the verse is
actually that way. It
says ונתן עליו, V'natan alav, ולקחו לטמא מעפר שריפת החטאת, V'lakchu latamei
mei'afar sreifas hachatas, take the ashes, ונתן עליו מים חיים אל כלי,
V'natan alav mayim chayim el keli, and put on it water, live
water, you know, well water, whatever, into the vessel. So the simple
read of the verse is that the ashes come first and then
the water. So ונתן עליו, V'natan alav, אמר אפר ברישא. Amar eifer
beresha. That's how you know ashes are first. So how do I
know the other thing, that the ashes can come second, and why
do the Rabbis assume the ashes always come second? והדר כתיב מים
חיים אל כלי. V'hadar ksiv mayim chayim el keli. Because we break
up the פסוק Pasuk and we only look at the end of
it. Okay. And we say מים חיים אל כלי, Mayim chayim el
keli, the juxtaposition of the water and the vessel, water to the
vessel, means the water has to be the first thing that hits
the vessel. So according to Rabbi Shimon, you could do either, either
ונתן עליו מים חיים, U'natan alav mayim chayim, which is you put
on the ashes the water, the ashes come first, or מים חיים
אל כלי, Mayim chayim el keli, the water first hits the vessel
and then the ashes. You could go either way. How about the
Rabbis? Why do, if they say the water has to be first,
what do they do with עליו? alav? So the Gemara says, הא
כיצד? Ha keitzad? I'm sorry, first, so how can that be? רצה
אפר למטה רצה אפר למעלה. Ratza efer lemata ratza efer lemala. You
can do either way, either ונתן עליו מים חיים, U'natan alav mayim
chayim, water on the ashes, or מים חיים אל כלי, Mayim chayim
el keli, the water has to hit the vessel first. ותנא דידן
מאי טעמא? Ve-tana didan mai ta'ama? And how about our Tanna, what's
his reasoning? אמר לך, Amar lach, סיפא דקרא דווקא. Seifa de-kra davka.
The end of the verse is, is telling you the real way
it has to be. מים חיים אל כלי. Mayim chayim el keli.
Water on ashes. ונתן עליו, Ve-natan alav, and so what does עליו
alav mean? לערבן. Le-arvan. It just means ונתן עליו Ve-natan alav meaning
that you have to mix the ashes and the water, you have
to mix them together well. But it doesn't literally mean that the
water goes on top of the ashes, it means that after you
get them together, the water should be on top of the ashes,
you have to mix them up well. All right, so again, it's
actually interesting because, you know, the Rabbi Shimon's position seems more פשט
pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. פשט Pshat of the פסוק pasuk seems
to be the water goes on the ashes, but חז"ל Chazal say...
Rabbi Shimon is often more פשט. pshat.
Is that true? I haven't noticed that. Okay, but חז"ל Chazal say
no, no, no, מים חיים אל כלי, Mayim chayim el keli, עליו
alav just means make sure they're all mixed together in the end.
Okay, so the Gemara now ends this up, then we're going to
go back to the Mishnah, but let's just finish this part. So,
where are we?
Okay, ונתן עליו לערבן. Ve-natan alav le-arvan. מאי חזית דסמכת אסיפא דקרא
דווקא אימא רישא דווקא? Mai chazit de-samchat a-seifa de-kra davka eima reisha
davka? Why did you emphasize the end of the פסוק pasuk and
then say עליו alav just means mix them up? Why not emphasize
the beginning of the פסוק pasuk and say that the, that the
water comes second? לא מצי אמרת. Lo matzi amrat. That you can't
say. ממה מצינו בכל מקום מכשיר למעלה. Mima matzinu be-chol makom machshir
lemala. In general, we assume that the key ingredient is put on
top. Okay, now what does it mean in general? Where's the in
general? So Rashi says, it's the other thing we're comparing it to,
the סוטה. Sotah. There the Torah is clear that the water is
first and the, and the dirt is later. So that which is
like the, you know, the sort of the מכשיר, machshir, because what
do you consider what's the מכשיר, machshir, which is the key ingredient?
So for some reason we're assuming again that the water is like
the base, it's not the special ingredient. So אף כאן מכשיר למעלה,
Af kan machshir lemala, here too it's above. Now, the question is,
what does this mean that that's our Mishnah? Right, our Mishnah basically
says that אין מי חטאת עושים מי חטאת, Ein mei chatat osim
mei chatat, right, which does, which means that you can't take the
mixture and add it to other water. So how is that related
at all to this debate of Rabbi Shimon and the Rabbanan? It
seems like the Gemara's reading it is that you can't take from
the mixture of this water and add it to ashes. Okay, but
if you have the ashes and you take the, you can't take
some of the מי חטאת mei chatat water and add it to
the ashes. And then the, the point it's telling you is why?
Because the water can't come first, the ashes... I mean, because the
ashes can't come first, the water has to come first. But again,
it seems like the simple sense of the Mishnah is not even
debated between the Rabbanan and Rabbi Shimon, it's just that it has
to come through ashes and water, not through taking מי חטאת mei
chatat water and adding it to other water. It could be that
the Gemara is emphasizing the end of the Mishnah, wait a minute,
yeah, it says אין מי חטאת עושים מי חטאת אלא עם מתן
אפר. Ein mei chatat osim mei chatat ela im matan efer. Which
is really emphasizing the end of the Mishnah of מתן אפר, matan
efer, which means that it's only through adding the, so you have
water, what it's saying, don't add מי חטאת mei chatat water to
this water, what do you have to add to the water? Ashes.
So it's saying, ah, that that emphasizes that you're adding the ashes
to the water and not the reverse, that is against Rabbi Shimon.
But again, the basic rule that you can't make מי חטאת mei
chatat by adding מי חטאת mei chatat to other water, that's really
agreed. The only debate here is when you have ashes and water,
does the order matter? Okay, let's take a look at the next
piece. We'll begin that. ואין בית הפרס עושה בית הפרס. Ve-ein beit
ha-peras oseh beit ha-peras. One בית הפרס beit ha-peras does not make
another one.
מתניתין דלא כרבי אליעזר. Matnitin de-lo ke-Rabbi Eliezer. Again, most of these
things are against Rabbi Eliezer it seems. דתנן, De-tnan, we learned in
the Mishnah,
רבי אליעזר אומר בית הפרס עושה בית הפרס. Rabbi Eliezer omer beit
ha-peras oseh beit ha-peras. That it can make a בית הפרס. beit
ha-peras. Apparently if you plow over one field, one field is already
plowed over and is a בית הפרס, beit ha-peras, and then you
plow from that field into another field, the other field does not
become a בית הפרס. beit ha-peras. Now the Gemara says actually, but
for one minute, I mean, obviously, does the whole
world become a בית הפרס beit ha-peras if we just keep on
plowing?
Well, that's an interesting question too, what's the limit for Rabbi Eliezer?
But I thought the question really which the Gemara asks is the
other way. All the other stuff we understand, but here, if there
really are little bits of bone and whatever in this field, how
can you ignore the fact that it might have got contaminated the
next field? So the Gemara actually assumes that the Rabbis actually do
admit that it might be a problem into the next field, just
not to the extent of Rabbi Eliezer. דרבנן עד כמה, De-rabbanan ad
kama, what would be the, how much would it contaminate for the
Rabbis? כי אתא רב דימי אמר ריש לקיש... Ki ata Rav Dimi
amar Reish Lakish... שלש שדות ושתי מענות, shalosh sadot u'shtei ma'anos, three
fields and two מענה ma'ane which is like a plowing unit. Now,
three fields mean the way רש"י Rashi understands you have your middle
field, and if you're plowing let's say in the horizontal direction, so
it's each field on the horizontal side. Or if you're plowing in
a vertical direction, I mean like north, south, east, west, it's each
field along the direction you're plowing. How much into the neighboring field?
It goes into the neighboring field the space of a מענה ma'ane
which is a plowing unit which is what? And this becomes a
מלוא מענה milo ma'ane what is that? מאה אמה, me'ah amah, a
hundred אמות, amos, which is not insignificant, it's about 150 feet. Because
we assume normally that that's the amount that's impacted if there's a
grave, 150 feet will be you know the
if it's disturbed can be where the stuff gets plowed into. כדתניא
k'detanya like we taught a ברייתא, braisa, העושה החורש את הקבר עושה
בית הפרס מלוא מענה מאה אמה. ha'oseh hachoresh es hakever oseh beis
hapras milo ma'ane me'ah amah. This is how בית הפרס beis hapras
is fundamentally made. It's if you plow over an area that then
you discover there was a grave there, you assume that the plow
could have taken pieces of the body to a hundred אמה amah
sort of you know which a surface radius or whatever in the
direction you were going. So here too, if there was a grave
somewhere in this field and you don't know where, and there might
have been you know it might have been at the edge of
the field, so you have to assume a hundred אמה amah in
each direction of plowing. Of course if that's true according to the
רבנן, Rabbanan, so basically a בית הפרס beis hapras is making a
בית הפרס beis hapras but okay we understand it. So then what's
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying? So רש"י Rashi says רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer is saying that you go in the fields in the opposite
direction as well. Right? Not only in this way but in this
way. So that's crazy, right? I mean right there's got to be
some logic to what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying if you're
not plowing in that direction why are you saying it? So תוספות
Tosafos says let me just quickly check read what תוספות Tosafos answer
is.
Oh, that the question is not about the neighboring field. There everybody
actually agrees. The question is the third field out. Okay? That when
if since רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that if the בית הפרס
beis hapras is עושה בית הפרס, oseh beis hapras, that's sort of
like תמורות עושה תמורות tmuros oseh tmuros etc. What it means is
we don't just consider this to be to be derivative of the
בית הפרס. beis hapras. We consider this to be a בית הפרס
beis hapras per se. And that means that you can daisy chain
it ad infinitum. Whereas the rabbis say no no no, it's only
the first degree removed and when you go further it will not
make another בית הפרס. beis hapras. To be continued.